{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "The aftermath of this event led to the creation of the Quadruple Alliance and the formation of the 38\nstate German Confederation. It restored the Bourbon Dynasty in France with Louis XVIII. This meeting\nwas interrupted by the Hundred Days and it was headed by Austrian minister Klemens von Metternich.\nFor ten points, name this 1815 meeting that sought to organize post-Napoleonic Europe.",
      "answer": "Congress of Vienna"
    },
    {
      "question": "This document calls one leader a “dread sovereign” and advocates to “combine ourselves together in\na civil body politic.” It was dated using the Julian Calendar instead of the Gregorian Calendar, and it\nwas recorded in a journal by William Bradford. For ten points, name this 1620 agreement signed by the\npilgrims who founded Plymouth Colony.",
      "answer": "Mayflower Compact"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2012, this man announced a “Return to Sovereignty” day. This man, who accused the show Asa\nZuba! of slander, leads a coalition between the NKP and his Liberal Democrats. He recently updated the\n“three-arrows” of his namesake economics but has been criticized for numerous visits to the Yasukuni\nShrine. For ten points, name this current Prime Minster of Japan.",
      "answer": [
        "Shinzo Abe",
        "Abe"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man received one appointment originally intended for Frederick Funston. Edward House\nprevented the official reprimand of this man for protesting a potential armistice to Supreme Allied\nCouncil. He was the first American to be promoted to General of the Armies during his lifetime, due to\nhis service commanding the American Expeditionary Force in World War I. For ten points, name this\nAmerican general, nicknamed “Black Jack.”",
      "answer": [
        "John Joseph “Black Jack” Pershing",
        "Pershing",
        "John J Pershing",
        "John Pershing"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A poem about this river notes that “Wushan’s clouds and rain” will be held back by “walls of\nstone.” Those walls predicted a dam, completed in 2012, that now blocks silt from traveling downstream,\npotentially weakening Shanghai on its mouth. The Three Gorges Dam was built on, for ten points, what\nlongest river in Asia?",
      "answer": [
        "Yangtze River",
        "Yangtze"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Marc Dubois suffered from this condition as the pilot of Air France Flight 447, which crashed in 2009.\nWorld records for this condition are no longer maintained due to fear of harm, but the last scientifically\ndocumented record for this condition is Randy Gardner’s 264 hours. Tracy Morgan was injured in a\nbus accident caused by a Walmart truck driver suffering from this condition. For ten points, name this\ncondition that causes irritability and yawning.",
      "answer": [
        "sleep deprivation",
        "insomnia",
        "fatigue",
        "exhaustion",
        "tiredness",
        "lack of sleep"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Theodore Parker and Gerrit Smith were part of the Secret Six that funded this man’s actions. The\nFugitive Slave Act prompted this man to create The League of the Gileadites. His son was killed by\nthe forces of John Reid in Osawatomie. The Sack of Lawrence prompted this man to participate in the\nPottawatomie Massacre. Robert E. Lee stopped this man from attempting to overtake a federal armory\nin West Virginia. For ten points, name this abolitionist who led an 1859 raid on Harper’s Ferry.",
      "answer": [
        "John Brown",
        "Brown"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This woman defeated the Emirate of Granada, ending the Reconquista period of her country. She\nsponsored the trips of an explorer from Genoa who started Spanish colonization of the New World. For\nten points, name this Castilian queen who married Ferdinand II of Aragon and sponsored the trips of\nChristopher Columbus.",
      "answer": [
        "Isabella I of Castille",
        "Isabella"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man gave the Appeal of 18 June Speech during one war. This leader’s opposition to the European\nCommission led to the Empty Chair Crisis. He was later criticized after Expo 67 for proclaiming “Long\nlive free Quebec!” This man’s government ended a conflict with the FLN by signing the Evian Accords.\nHe was brought to power in the May Crisis, leading to the formation of the Fifth Republic. For ten points,\nname this French Prime Minister who led the Free French Forces during WWII.",
      "answer": [
        "Charles de Gaulle",
        "Gaulle"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Xerxes the Great built a throne hall with one hundred of these features in Persepolis. The term\nentasis refers to the gradual decrease in these objects’ diameter as they rise, removing the optical illusion\nthat these objects bend inward. One style of these objects uses a scroll for the capital; in addition to that\nIonic type, these objects come in Doric and Corinthian orders. For ten points, name these architectural\nelements which usually bear the weight of a roof or ceiling.",
      "answer": [
        "columns",
        "column",
        "pillar",
        "pillars"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What American state is home to the world’s largest coin mint and, with Washington,\nlegalized marijuana growing in 2012?",
      "answer": "Colorado"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During a drunken brawl, this man killed his officer Cleitus the Black, who had earlier saved this\nman’s life during the Battle of the Granicus River. This man’s successors were known as the Diadochi\n[dee-AH-doh-kee], and this rider of Bucephalus defeated Darius III at the Battle of Gaugamela. For ten\npoints, name this son of Phillip II, a king of Macedon who conquered Persia.",
        "answer": "Alexander the Great"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Alexander the Great was tutored as a youth by this man, who established the Lyceum and wrote\nNicomachean Ethics.",
        "answer": "Aristotle"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the Battle of this location, Bernard Coy was able to sneak into its armory and secure a\nSpringfield rifle. Robert Franklin Stroud was labeled its Birdman, and a group led by Frank Morris are\npresumed to have drowned after escaping this location in San Francisco Bay. For ten points, name this\nnotorious island prison.",
        "answer": [
          "Alcatraz Federal Penitentiary",
          "Alcatraz",
          "Alcatraz Island"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After accusations of receiving special treatment, this Chicago gangster known as “Scarface” was\nmoved to Alcatraz prison.",
        "answer": [
          "Alphonse Gabriel “Al” Capone",
          "Capone",
          "Al Capone"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2000, Robert Fowler reported how the trade of these objects violated the Lusaka Protocol. The\nKimberley Process ensures that these objects are “conflict-free.” The Revolutionary United Front in Sierra\nLeone used child soldiers to gather these objects. These objects are sold by the Cecil Rhodes-founded\ncompany De Beers. For ten points, name these precious gems that are often nicknamed “blood” when\nused to finance warlords.",
        "answer": [
          "blood diamonds",
          "diamond"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Marange fields, one of the largest diamond-producing regions in the world, are found in\nwhat country once called Southern Rhodesia?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic of Zimbabwe",
          "Zimbabwe"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2008, FiveThirtyEight.com only failed to predict this state’s Presidential result. Robert Kennedy’s\nspeech after the death of Martin Luther King was given in this state, shortly after speeches that day at\nBall State and Notre Dame universities here. In 2015, the review website Angie’s List cancelled a planned\nexpansion of its headquarters in this state after the Religious Freedom Restoration Act was passed and\nsigned by its governor, Mike Pence. For ten points, name this “Hoosier” state.",
        "answer": "Indiana"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This statistician and founder of FiveThirtyEight rebounded in 2012 to correctly predict the\nentire electoral college.",
        "answer": [
          "Nate Silver",
          "Silver"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Alcuin of York’s letters lament these people’s sacking of a priory on the Northumbrian island of\nLindisfarne. The Great Heathen Army legendarily avenged the death of one of their leaders, Ragnar\nLodbrok. Leif Erikson founded their colony of Vinland in the New World. For ten points, name these\nScandinavian sea-faring raiders whose longships dominated medieval Europe for four centuries.",
        "answer": "Vikings"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "True to his name, this legendary discoverer of Greenland was Leif Erikson’s father.",
        "answer": [
          "Eric the Red",
          "Eric Thorvaldsson"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A “tattered man” in this novel bothers the protagonist, who is given a yellow envelope to deliver to\nWilson’s family upon his death, though Wilson asks for it back. In this novel, Henry Fleming is hit in the\nhead with a rifle, leading his fellow soldiers to think he suffered the title wound. For ten points, name this\nCivil War novel written by Stephen Crane.",
        "answer": "The Red Badge of Courage"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Two years before publishing The Red Badge of Courage, Crane wrote Maggie, A Girl of the\nStreets, which is set in the streets and flophouses of this city’s Bowery neighborhood.",
        "answer": [
          "New York City",
          "NYC",
          "New York"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these people is the title character of an opera which was revised to add a “Polish act” and ends\nwith the Holy Fool lamenting his country’s fate in Kromy Forest. In another opera, Ivan Susanin sacrifices\nhimself for this title leader. The lead-up to the Time of Troubles was chronicled in Modest Mussorgsky’s\nopera about one of these monarchs, Boris Godunov. For ten points, Mikhail Glinka wrote an opera about\nA Life For what leaders of the Russian Empire?",
        "answer": [
          "tsars",
          "tsar"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov’s opera The Tale of Tsar Saltan is best known for what virtuosic\norchestral excerpt in which the Tsar’s son is changed into an insect?",
        "answer": "Flight of the Bumblebee"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The “liquidators” dealt with the aftermath of this event, which was detected after a day in Forsmark,\nSweden. The Red Forest was created by this event, which led to a “zone of alienation” being marked\naround the city of Pripyat. It was triggered by a poorly-safeguarded experiment in which control rods\nwere manually removed, spreading radiation over much of Europe. For ten points, name this 1986 nuclear\nmeltdown in modern Ukraine.",
        "answer": [
          "Chernobyl nuclear disaster",
          "Chernobyl"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Chernobyl disaster was a major catalyst towards this Soviet premier’s adoption of glasnost,\na policy of openness and government transparency.",
        "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "HOLY CITIES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "the Masjid al-Haram and the Kaaba, the holiest site in Islam?",
          "answer": "Mecca"
        },
        {
          "question": "Solomon’s Temple and the Dome of the Rock in Israel?",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "the birthplace of Jesus and the Church of the Nativity?",
          "answer": "Bethlehem"
        },
        {
          "question": "the childhood home of Jesus in Galilee?",
          "answer": "Nazareth"
        },
        {
          "question": "home to over 1,000 Buddhist shrines built while it was the capital of Japan?",
          "answer": "Kyoto"
        },
        {
          "question": "the burial place of Muhammad, the second-holiest city in Islam?",
          "answer": "Medina"
        },
        {
          "question": "the Golden Temple, which houses the Adi Granth, the Sikh holy scripture?",
          "answer": "Amritsar"
        },
        {
          "question": "the Baha’i World Centre and the Bab’s burial place on Mount Carmel?",
          "answer": "Haifa"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Which holy city is or was home to..."
    },
    {
      "category": "13 AMERICAN COLONIES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Included the first permanent English settlement at Jamestown?",
          "answer": "Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of the Mayflower landing?",
          "answer": "Massachusetts"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the site of the earlier failed “Lost Colony” of Roanoke?",
          "answer": "North Carolina"
        },
        {
          "question": "Originally included the counties of Cornwall, Albany, Kings, and Queens?",
          "answer": "New York"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was founded as a colony for Quakers?",
          "answer": "Pennsylvania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included Providence Plantations?",
          "answer": "Rhode Island"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was founded last, by James Oglethorpe as a debtor’s prison?",
          "answer": "Georgia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was owned by the noble Calvert family?",
          "answer": "Maryland"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Which of the 13 original American colonies..."
    },
    {
      "category": "BRITISH CELEBRITIES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is the longest-reigning monarch?",
          "answer": [
            "Queen Elizabeth II",
            "Elizabeth II"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the divorced wife of Prince Charles, who was killed in a 1997 car crash?",
          "answer": [
            "Diana",
            "Diana Spencer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the Cambridge physicist who has studied black holes for decades despite suffering from ALS?",
          "answer": [
            "Stephen Hawking",
            "Hawking"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the retired Manchester United midfielder and national team captain known for “bending” his free\nkicks?",
          "answer": [
            "David Beckham",
            "Beckham"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the frontman and writer of “Bohemian Rhapsody” for Queen?",
          "answer": [
            "Freddie Mercury",
            "Mercury"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the silent film star who directed and starred in The Great Dictator?",
          "answer": [
            "Sir Charlie Chaplin",
            "Chaplin",
            "Charlie Chaplin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was praised for his leadership during the failed 1914 Endurance expedition?",
          "answer": [
            "Sir Ernest Shackleton",
            "Shackleton"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the naturalist producer and narrator of Life on Earth and brother of actor Richard?",
          "answer": [
            "Sir David Attenborough",
            "David Attenborough",
            "Attenborough"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Who..."
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man described the arrival of the first African slaves into his home colony in a\nletter to Edwin Sandys. This man, who traveled with his family back to England on the\nship (20 pts) ",
        "Treasurer, created the Varina Farms plantation and married a woman christened (10 pts) ",
        "Rebecca after her conversion to Christianity. For ten points, name this early American settler who\ndeveloped tobacco as a cash crop in Virginia and married Pocahontas."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "John Rolfe",
        "Rolfe"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Some of this company’s Turbocharged Direct Injection, or TDI, engines controversially\ndid not require the use of AdBlue urea solution to control the production of (20 pts) ",
        "nitrogen\noxides. In September 2015, this company’s use of “defeat device” software was revealed\nwhen the EPA charged this company with (10 pts) ",
        "cheating on emission testing with hundreds of\nthousands of its diesel-powered cars. For ten points, name this German automaker of the Golf, Jetta, and\nBeetle, whose name loosely translates to “People’s Car.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Volkswagen Group",
        "Volkswagen"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1855, Napoleon III commissioned a classification system for this commodity, produced\nby Haut-Brion and Chateau Margaux. Prominent (20 pts) ",
        "growing regions for this product\ninclude France’s “golden slope,” though the 1976 Judgment of Paris proved the quality of (10 pts) ",
        "California’s production of varieties like Cabernet Sauvignon. For ten points, name this alcoholic\nbeverage produced in Burgundy and Bordeaux from grapes."
      ],
      "answer": "wine"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Foreigners such as the Scotsman Thomas Gordon were often invited to lead this\norganization. One portion of this organization nearly sparked (20 pts) ",
        "war with Great Britain\nwhile being deployed to relieve another part of this organization, which had been bottled up\nin Port Arthur. That force would proceed to have its T crossed by (10 pts) ",
        "Heihachiro Togo and\nbe destroyed at the Battle of Tsushima Straits. The Baltic and Pacific fleets were part of, for ten points,\nwhat military organization, which experienced a revolt on the battleship Potemkin?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Imperial Russian Navy",
        "Russian Navy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Mediation in this agreement was performed by Cyrus Vance. This agreement affirmed\nthe importance of UN Security Council Resolution 242. (20 pts) ",
        "Tensions rose after its signing\ndue to assumption of King Hussein’s willingness to agree to its terms. It led to a framework\nfor the eventual return of the Sinai Peninsula. (10 pts) ",
        "Menachem Begin and Anwar Sadat shared the\n1978 Nobel Peace Prize shortly after signing, for ten points, what agreement between Israel and Egypt\nguided by Jimmy Carter at a presidential retreat?"
      ],
      "answer": "Camp David Accords"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A parrot rests on a sign in one work by this artist, in which a cat, an ox, a rabbit, and\nan elk represent the Four Humors. A demon under a rainbow holds a sign bearing the title\nof this artist’s (20 pts) ",
        "Melencolia I. This artist incorrectly added a horn to his depiction of an\nanimal that had been given to Lisbon by Indian diplomats in 1515, and showed (10 pts) ",
        "Famine,\nWar, Plague, and Death trampling peasants in another work. For ten points, name this German creator\nof woodcuts like the Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse and Rhinoceros."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Albrecht Durer",
        "Durer"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man threatened to kill Dennis Wilson, a Beach Boy, for changing the lyrics to his\nsong “Cease to Exist.” Vincent Bugliosi used circumstantial evidence to convict this man of\nconspiracy to (20 pts) ",
        "murder. He predicted a chaotic white vs. black war triggered by his music\nand that of the (10 pts) ",
        "Beatles; this man called that conflict Helter Skelter. For ten points, name this man\nwho, in 1969, ordered Sharon Tate and eight other people to be murdered by his so-called “Family.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Charles Manson",
        "Manson"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Thomas Percy and Charles Neville attempted to overthrow this monarch in the Rising\nof the North. This monarch supported the Dutch in one conflict by signing the Treaty of\nNonsuch, and Francis Walsingham uncovered a plot to assassinate this monarch by Anthony (20 pts) ",
        "Babington, which led to the execution of this monarch’s cousin, Mary Stuart. This\nmonarch spoke of having a “heart and stomach of a (10 pts) ",
        "king” in a speech to troops at Tilbury.\nThe Spanish Armada targeted, for ten points, what “Virgin Queen” of England?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Elizabeth I of England",
        "Elizabeth I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Artist George Catlin specialized in portraiture of these people. J.P. Morgan\nfunded Edward Curtis’ project to photographically document the lives of these\npeople. Korczak Ziolkowski began sculpting a (20 pts) ",
        "monument to one of these people\nin 1948; that unfinished monument is less than twenty miles from Mount Rushmore\non the (10 pts) ",
        "sacred Thunderhead Mountain. For ten points, name these people, including Crazy\nHorse, a member of the Oglala Sioux."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Native Americans",
        "American Indians"
      ]
    }
  ]
}